Lotte Jacobi Collection
Lotte Jacobi Collection
1930-1990
1967-1969
Gropper family.
0.5 linear ft.
Correspondence, clippings, photographs
4974141
Biographical History
Johanna Alexandra "Lotte" Jacobi (1886-1990) was a German-American photographer. Born in Prussia, she studied in Poland and Germany and began photographing professionally in the mid 1920s. She left Germany in 1935 for the United States, where she remained for the rest of her life. She was known for her portraits as well as her "photogenics," a technique that involved creating pictures without the use of a camera by exposing photosensitive paper to light, shadow, objects, etc. Her primary archives, including some 47,000 negatives, are held at the University of New Hampshire. She was friends with Joseph and Vera Gropper, and corresponded with them and their children over many years
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Lotte Jacobi Collection, accumulated by the Gropper family, consists of correspondence, photographs, and printed material.
Correspondence contains letters from Jacobi to Joseph and Vera Gropper and their family.
Photographs consists almost entirely of postcards printed with photographs by Jacobi, including her iconic photograph of Albert Einstein. Most are portraits, but there are also a few examples of her photogenics. There are also three photographs of Jacobi herself, and a picture of German expressionist painter Max Pechstein and his wife, in his studio.
Printed material contains books, clippings (including obituaries), and exhibit catalogs.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically. Photo postcards are arranged in the order received, to match the accompanying list of titles. Printed material is arranged alphabetically by type or title.
Related Material
The Lotti Jacobi Papers, consisting of 72 boxes and some 47,000 negatives, are held by the University of New Hampshire.
Subject and Genre Headings
Photography; Beckers, Marion, Lotte Jacobi: Berlin-New York.; Gropper, Joseph.; Gropper, Vera.; Jacobi, Lotte, 1896-1990.; Atelier Lotte Jacobi: Berlin-New York.; Photographers.; Photography, Artistic.; Portrait photography.; Women photographers.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Photographic postcards.; Photographs.; Photographers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dawna (Gropper) Snyder
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Gropper family (Joseph, Vera, Dawna, Chris), 1969-1972 (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - by Jacobi
    - Einstein Portfolio, 14 Mar 1979; 25 reproductions in printed grey four-flap enclosure (Box 1)
    - Photographs postcards, to Groppers, includes list of image titles, provided by donor (Box 1)
    - Photographs postcards, not written on, includes list of image titles, provided by donor; one is a self-portrait of Jacobi (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1930; 1932; Max Pechstein and wife; "Madonna," Stalinabad (Box 1)
  - of Jacobi, 1982; undated (Box 1)
- Printed material
  - Books
    - Lotte Jacobi: Berlin-New York, by Marion Beckers and Elisabeth Moorgat, Nicolaische Verlagsbuchhandlung Beuermann Gmb, 1998; hardcover edition, with jacket (Box 1)
    - Lotte Jacobi, by James Fasanelli and Lotte Jacobi, Addison House, 1978; publisher's catalog with description of book (Box 1)
  - Clippings about, 1976-1980; 1987,; 1990; includes obituaries; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Exhibit, 1973; 1977-1978 (Box 1)